Finding Aid for Esson M. Gale papers, 1909-1965
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Esson M. Gale papers 1909-1965
Gale, Esson McDowell, 1884-
3 linear feet and 1 oversize folder
851311 Aa 2; UAm
Orientalist, government official and director of the International Center at University of Michigan. Correspondence, 1929-1965, notebooks, 1940-1942, and scrapbooks relating largely to professional activities and China; also photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Esson M. Gale and his wife (donor no. 3225 ) and came to the library in various accessions, 1956-1967.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Esson M. Gale was born in Bad Axe, Mich., December 8, 1884. He received his B.A. (1907) and M.A. (1908) degrees from the University of Michigan and his doctorate at the University of Leyden, Holland. His specialty was Chinese language studies. Gale first went to China as a government language student interpreter following his graduation from the University of Michigan in 1908. He spent five years in the U.S. Consular Service in Peking and Shanghai; he would later become commissioner of the Chinese Salt Revenue Administration. He returned to the U-M in 1927 as visiting lecturer in Far Eastern history. He was lecturer and chairman of the department of oriental languages and literature at the University of California (Berkeley) from 1928 to 1932 and visiting professor of political science at Northwestern University in 1940-41. In 1942, he became acting James Orin Murfin Professor of Political Science at the University of Michigan in 1942. In 1943, he was named to be second director of the International Center. He retired in 1955. Later, from 1958 to 1960, he would be visiting professor at Korea University. He died May 15, 1964.
The Gale collection is arranged into the following series: Biographical Information; Correspondence; Conferences and other activities; Miscellaneous; Photographs. Within the correspondence, there are letters from Adolf Berle, James A. Farley, Joseph R. Hayden, Hubert H. Humphrey, Frank Murphy, Chester Nimitz, Singhman Rhee, Daniel Poling, John Powell, Arthur H. Vandenberg, and Wendell Willkie. Some of the photos were collected during Gale's employment in China (1909-1927) and Korea (1958-1959), and photos relating to the University of Michigan Class of 1907, the Quadrangle Club, and the International Center.
Subjects:
China--History--Republic, 1912-1949.; Missionaries--China.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. International Center.; World War, 1939-1945.; China--History--1949-1976.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
China--History--Republic, 1912-1949.; Korea.; Quadrangle Club (University of Michigan); Soldiers.; University of Michigan. Class of 1907.; University of Michigan. International Center.; China--History--1861-1912.
Contributors:
Berle, Adolf Augustus, 1895-1971.; Farley, James A. (James Aloysius), 1888-1976.; Hayden, Joseph Ralston, 1887-1945.; Humphrey, Hubert H. (Hubert Horatio), 1911-1978.; Murphy, Frank, 1890-1949.; Nimitz, Chester W. (Chester William), 1885-1966.; Poling, Daniel A. (Daniel Alfred), 1884-1968.; Powell, John.; Rhee, Syngman, 1875-1965.; Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951.; Willkie, Wendell L. (Wendell Lewis), 1892-1944.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Biographical Information
  - Biographical and bibliographical information (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Undated, 1929 and 1934-1965, 17 folders (Box 1)
- Conferences and other activities
  - Institute of Public Affairs, University of Virginia, 1940 (Box 2)
  - Conference on Religion, University of Michigan, July 1940 (Box 2)
  - Occasional lectures on the Far East, 1940 (Box 2)
  - Social Studies, 1941 (Box 2)
    (lectures, outlines and reviews)
  - China in World War II, 1941-1942 (Box 2)
    (includes letters from William J. Donovan)
  - University of Michigan in World Affairs (proposal and manuscript) (Box 2)
  - Salt for the Dragon
    - Draft (Box 2)
    - Correspondence with publisher and with individuals receiving the book (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous
  - Chronological, 1928-1960 and undated, 6 folders (Box 2)
    (include speeches and speech announcements)
  - Journey to Chunking, China, 1942, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Chinese student survey, 1953 (Box 2)
  - English translation of La Chine Antique, undated (Box 2)
- Photographs
  - China, 1909-1927
    (see also oversize folder UAm)
    - Gale with others (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Korea, 1958-1959 (Box 2)
  - University of Michigan and miscellaneous (Box 2)
- Scrapbooks, clippings, and published materials
  - Reprints of articles (Box 3)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1920-1964 (Box 3)
  - "Photo sketch of Manchukuo" (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook, 1941-1952 (Box 3)
    (mainly clippings and program announcements for Gale lectures(
  - Scrapbook relating to testimonial dinner for Esson M. Gale, 1953 (Box 3)
  - Articles by Gale from Journal of Asiatic Studies, the Asiatic Research Bulletin, etc. (Box 3)
Selective Index to Correspondents
Berle, Adolf Augustus, 1895-1971.
Jan. 15, 1944
Farley, James Aloysius, 1888-
May 26, 1960
Hayden, Joseph Ralston, 1887-1945.
Oct. 27, 1941
Humphrey, Hubert H. (Hubert Horatio), 1911-1978.
Nov. 30, 1959
Murphy, Frank, 1890-1949.
June 23, 1946
Nimitz, Chester W. (Chester William), 1885-1966.
Jan. 10, 1939, June 1946, Oct. 10, 1946
Poling, Daniel A. (Daniel Alfred), 1884-1968.
Dec. 12, 1961
Powell, John.
May 8, 1946
Rhee, Syngman, 1875-1965.
Sept. 21, 1945
Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951.
Nov. 12, 1946
Willkie, Wendell L. (Wendell Lewis), 1892-1944.
Aug. 31, 1943